Register of the Ardashīr Zāhidī papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Photographs, circa 1915-2000s
  - Nowruz albums, 1973-1975
    - Sheraton-Park Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1974 March 20 (Box 228, Folder 4-6, Box 229, Folder 1)
      Includes photographs of Mr. and Mrs. Abdullah Malikyar.
    - Society of Iranians in New York, 1974 March (Box 229, Folder 2-3)
    - Society of Iranians in Texas, 1975 March (Box 230, Folder 1, Box 229, Folder 4-5)
    - 1975 March (Box 230, Folder 2-5)
    - Society of Iranians in Los Angeles, 1975 March (Box 231, Folder 1-2)
    - Society of Iranians in San Francisco, 1975 March (Box 231, Folder 3-4)
    - Society of Iranians in Chicago, 1975 March (Box 231, Folder 5-6)
    - Hilton Hotel, 1975 March (Box 232, Folder 1)
    - Society of Iranians in Utah, 1975 March (Box 232, Folder 2-4)
    - Society of Iranians in Massachusetts, 1975 March (Box 233, Folder 1-4, Box 232, Folder 5-6)
- Art, 1958-1976
  - Shahnaz Pahlavi etching, 1958 (Box 252)
  - Drawing of a tank, 1958 June (Box 252)
  - Persepolis prints, 1976 (Box 252)
    By Claude E. Hooton.
- Clippings File, 1956-1979
  Albums of clippings that document Zahedi's activities and Iran-related news.
  - Chronological
    - British newspapers, 1956-1973 (Box 260)
    - Iran Times, 1971-1974 (Box 261)
      Nowruz gift.
    - 1972-1973 (Box 261)
    - State visit, 1973 July (Boxes 262-266)
      In four parts.
    - Ardeshir Zahedi, 1974 January-June (Box 267)
    - Shah in Paris, 1974 June 24-27 (Box 268)
    - Black tie dinner for the American Ballet Theater, 1976 April 7-18 (Box 234, Folder 1-3)
    - Elizabeth Taylor, 1976 May (Box 269)
    - Hanafi Siege, 1977 March (Boxes 270-271)
      In two parts.
  - Ambassador clippings
    Original numbering maintained; album 25 appears to be missing.
    - 1, 1973 June 26 (Box 272)
    - 2, 1973 December - 1974 February (Box 273)
    - 3, 1972 December - 1973 June (Box 274)
    - 4, 1974 January-April (Box 275)
    - 5, 1974 March -June (Box 276)
    - 6, 1974 August-October (Box 277)
    - 7, 1974 October-December (Box 278)
    - 8, 1974 June-August (Box 279)
    - 9, 1975 January (Box 280)
      Issue of National Geographic.
    - 10, 1975 January-February (Box 281)
    - 11, 1975 February (Box 282)
    - 12, 1975 February-March (Box 283)
    - 13, 1975 March-May (Box 284)
    - 14, 1975 May-July (Box 285)
    - 15, 1975 July-September (Box 286)
    - 16, 1975 March-November (Box 287)
    - 17, 1975 November - 1976 February (Box 288)
    - 18, 1976 February-April (Box 289)
    - 19, 1976 April-May (Box 290)
    - 20, 1976 May (Box 291)
    - 21, 1976 June-July (Box 292)
    - 22, 1976 August-November (Box 293)
    - 23, 1976 November - 1977 March (Box 294)
    - 24, 1977 February-April (Box 295)
    - 26, 1977 July-December (Box 296)
    - 27, 1977 December - 1978 June (Box 297)
    - 28, 1978 June - 1979 January (Box 298)
  - Persian clippings
    - 1351 Day māh-Isfand māh, 1972 December - 1973 March (Box 299)
    - 1352 Farvardīn māh-1353 Murdād māh, 1973 March - 1974 July (Box 300)
    - 1353 Murdād māh-Isfand māh, 1974 August - 1975 March (Box 301)
    - 2535 Farvardīn māh-Khurdād māh, 1976 April-June (Box 302)
    - 1355 Bahman māh-Isfand māh, 1977 January-March (Box 303)
    - 1356 Farvardīn māh-Shahrīvar māh, 1977 March-September (Box 304)
    - 1356 Mihr māh-Ābān māh, 1977 September-November (Box 305)
    - 1356 Ābān māh-Day māh, 1977 November-December (Box 306)
    - 1356 Day māh - Isfand māh, 1977 December-1978 March (Box 307)
    - 1357 Farvardīn māh-Shahrīvar māh, 1978 March-September (Box 308)
    - 1357 Shahrīvar māh-Day māh, 1978 September-December (Box 309)
- Moving Images, 1971-2009
  Computer disks.
  - "His Excellency Ardeshir Zahedi's Visit to Bahrain,", 1971 (Reading room Workstation)
    Ardeshir's visit to Bahrain and meetings with government officials, including Isa bin Salman Al Khalifa. DVD.
  - Ardeshir Zahedi interview with Walter Cronkite, 1979 January 22 (Reading room Workstation)
    Ardeshir discusses the Iranian Revolution and overthrow of the Shah, and political developments in Iran. DVD.
  - Interview, "Hardtalk," BBC, 2009 August 26 (Reading room Workstation)
    به عبارت دیگر: گفتگو با اردشیر زاهدی
    Ardeshir discusses events surrounding the 1953 Mordad. DVD.
- Sound Recordings, 1977-1992
  - Ardeshir Zahedi interview with Mike Wallace, circa 1977 (Reading room Workstation)
    Mostly about Savak operations in the United States. Cassette tape.
  - "As I Recall: The Events that Changed the Course of the History," interview with BBC correspondent Andrew Whitely, 1992 August 22 (Reading room Workstation)
    Ardeshir discusses memories of the Iranian Revolution, the Shah, and his visit to Iran in 1978. Other topics include Black Friday, General Robert E. Huyser's mission to Iran, Shah's death. CD-R.
- Oversize Material, 1976
  - Ardeshir Zahedi Circus Saints and Sinners sign, 1976 September
- Incremental Materials, circa 1920s-2016
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, writings, photographs, video and recordings, computer disks, and printed material, mostly from Zahedi’s time in Switzerland. A few materials are related to Fazlollah Zahedi’s political career and Ardeshir Zahedi’s second appointment as Ambassador to the United States, but the bulk of the material stems from his time in Switzerland, and includes drafts and photographs and documents assembled for his multi-volume memoir. More recent photographs portray public appearances, and his family and social life. Zahedi is also an active public figure, and his numerous television and radio appearances are documented in the video and sound recordings. The printed material includes Persian language magazines, many of which feature Zahedi, and Persian language books, mostly about the Pahlavi period.
  - Faz̤l Allāh Zāhidī Papers, undated
    - Notes in Persian, undated (Box-folder 310: 1)
  - Ambassador to the United States File, 1951-1977
    Includes official reports and notes related to correspondence.
    - Reports, 1951-1972 (Box-folder 310: 2-4)
      Includes economic and foreign policy reports related to Iran, the United States, and American-Iranian relations.
    - Discussions with Senators, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 310: 5)
      Notes in Persian.
  - Biographical File, 1957-2016
    Includes award dedications, news features, interview transcripts, and biographical notes spanning multiple decades. The calendar file includes Zahedi's monthly appointment calendar from 2004-2014, with the exception of the years 2009 and 2013, which appear to be missing.
    - Awards, 2002-2016 (Box-folder 310: 6)
    - Calendar file
      - Telephone and address book, undated (Box-folder 310: 7)
      - Telephone log, undated (Box-folder 310: 8)
      - Calendars, 2004-2014 (Box-folder 310: 9-13, Box-folder 311: 1-5)
    - Clippings, 1957-2010, undated
      - General, 1957-2010, undated (Box-folder 311: 6-10)
      - Rah-E-Zendegi, 2002-2013 (Box-folder 312: 1-2, Box-folder 311: 11-12)
    - Interviews, 1984, 2007-2012 (Box-folder 312: 3)
    - Personal website, 2006 (Box-folder 312: 4)
  - Correspondence, 1976-2013, undated
    Includes letters sent and received, written in both Persian and English.
    - Various Correspondents (Box-folder 312: 5-10)
    - Absalti, Pari (Box-folder 312: 11)
    - Afshar, Shirin (Box-folder 312: 12)
    - Ahrar, Ahmad (Box-folder 312: 13)
    - Amouzegar, Parviz (Box-folder 312: 14)
    - Bakhtiyar, Hooman (Box-folder 312: 15)
      Includes photocopies of declassified documents, circa 1972-1973.
    - Beale, Betty (Box-folder 312: 16)
    - Cooper, Andrew Scott (Box-folder 312: 17)
    - Danielle (Box-folder 312: 18)
    - Derakhshani, Farrokh (Box-folder 313: 1, Box-folder 312: 19)
    - Etemad, Akbar (Box-folder 313: 2)
    - Ghaffari, Abbas (Box-folder 313: 3)
    - Ghassemi, Reza (Box-folder 313: 4)
    - Guppy, Brian (Box-folder 313: 5)
    - Honarmand, Manuchehr (Box-folder 313: 6)
    - Imperial Inspectorate Organization (Box-folder 313: 7)
    - Juhanpour, Farhang (Box-folder 313: 8-10)
    - Milani, Abbas (Box-folder 313: 11)
    - Pye, Michael (Box-folder 313: 12)
    - Rah-E-Zendegi (Box-folder 313: 13)
    - Shirzad, Farhad (Box-folder 313 :14-17)
    - Tehrani, Ahmad (Box-folder 313: 18)
    - Zahedi, Nazli (Box-folder 313: 19)
  - Writings, 2004-2013, undated
    - Articles and opinion pieces, 2000-2017 (Box-folder 314: 1)
    - Edited works, undated
      - "His Excellency Mr. A. R. Ansari Memoir,", undated (Box-folder 314: 2-3)
        Text in Persian.
    - "Five Decisive Days,", undated (Box-folder 314: 4)
      Undated memoir account written for the Ettila'at newspaper publisher titled "Five Decisive Days: August 14-18, 1953."
    - Memoirs, 2004-2013, undated
      - Volume I - Draft in Persian, undated (Box-folder 314: 5-9, Box-folder 315: 1-6)
        Photocopies of typed and handwritten pages, with notes and edits in margins.
      - Photocopies and Corrections, undated (Box-folder 315: 7)
        Photocopies of photographs and accompanying notes, as well as material related to the book jacket for Volume I. Also includes a document with partial corrections, presumably for Volume I.
      - Draft in Persian, undated (Box-folder 315: 8, Box-folder 316: 1)
        Two folders, possibly with two separate drafts, one dated 2003 and the other undated.
      - Notes and articles, 2012, undated (Box-folder 316: 2)
        Includes handwritten notes and news articles related to memoirs.
      - Printouts, 2012 (Box-folder 316: 3)
      - English translations, 2010 (Box-folder 316: 4-5)
        Includes English translations of various sections and chapters of Volume II.
      - Notes and articles, 2004-2013 (Box-folder 316: 6)
        Includes articles, book reviews, and other published material relevant to memoirs. Also includes material related to the front cover of Volume I.
      - Review of Volume I, 2006 (Box-folder 316: 7)
        Includes a review of Volume I by Mohammad Pourdad.
      - English translations, undated (Box-folder 316: 8)
        Includes English translation of various chapters.
      - Volume I book jacket, 2012 (Box-folder 316: 9)
      - Articles, 1961, undated (Box-folder 316: 10)
        Includes copies of articles relevant to memoirs.
      - Volume I - English translation, undated (Box-folder 316: 11)
        Contains English translation of various chapters.
      - Volume I - English translation with notes, 2011 (Box-folder 316: 12)
        Contains English translation of various chapters with notes attached.
      - Volume I - English translation with notes and CD-R, 2007 (Box-folder 317: 1)
        Contains English translation of various chapters with notes attached. See Digital files series for CD-R's included with this file.
      - Article, 2011 (Box-folder 317: 2)
        Contains article titled "The Shah's Spleen: Its Impact on History" by Leon Morgenstern.
      - Volume II - Draft in Persian, undated (Box-folder 317: 3)
        Photocopies of typed and handwritten pages, with notes attached and edits in margins.
      - "Printed Matter,", circa 2005 (Box-folder 317: 4)
        Includes photocopies in Persian, possibly memoir chapters or photo captions. Also includes a copy of a photograph featuring the Shah at Chatsworth, dated 1962.
      - Articles and documents, 1961, undated (Box-folder 317: 5)
        Includes copies of White House memoranda and other related material.
      - Photographs and reprints, circa 1953-2003 (Box-folder 317: 7-9)
        Includes photographs and photographic reprints of Fazlollah and Pahlavis.
      - Photocopies, undated (Box-folder 317: 10)
        Photocopies of photographs.
      - Clippings, documents, and photos, circa 1953-2001 (Box-folder 317: 11-12)
        Includes photographs and reprints as well as news clippings about the Shah, copies of White House memoranda, and other related documents.
      - Volume I - Draft in Persian, 2006 (Box-folder 318: 1)
        Complete draft of Volume I with notes attached and edits in margins.
      - Volume II - Draft in Persian, circa 2009 (Box-folder 318: 2)
        Complete draft of Volume II with notes attached and edits in margins.
      - Volume I - English translation with notes, 2012 May 25 (Box-folder 318: 3)
        Complete translation of Volume I with notes. The version is identified as "Version May 25, 2012."
    - Notes, undated (Box-folder 318: 4-11, Box-folder 319: 1)
      Includes loose documents and assorted notebooks with clippings and articles attached. Notes in Persian and English. Also includes folder with correspondence and transcripts related to memoirs.
    - Speeches and interviews, 1973-1978 (Box-folder 319: 2-4)
      Contains collected transcripts.
  - Subject File, 1977-2012, undated
    Includes articles and notes related to various subjects. Some correspondence and photos included as well.
    - Basir Divan, undated (Box-folder 320: 1)
    - Hanafi Siege, 1977, 2011 (Box-folder 320: 2)
    - Iran, circa 2011-2012 (Box-folder 320: 3)
      Contains collected articles on politics, history, and current events in Iran. Articles in both Persian and English.
    - Iran Nuclear Program; Non-Proliferation Treaty, circa 2011-2012 (Box-folder 320: 4)
    - ISIS, undated (Box-folder 320: 5)
    - Persian Gulf, 2006 (Box-folder 320: 6)
    - Fuad Ruhani, 2011 (Box-folder 320: 7)
    - The Shah, Abbas Milani, 2005, 2011 (Box-folder 320: 8)
    - Fazlollah Zahedi, 2006, undated (Box-folder 320: 9)
  - Photographs, circa 1910-2016
    Contain a combination of photographic prints, reproductions, and clippings, gathered for Zahedi’s memoirs. Many of the pictures are accompanied by notes.
    - Albums, 1910-2016
      - Memoir albums, 1910-2010
        - Fazlollah's youth; school; Beirut; United States; Point Four Program, 1910-1951 (Box-folder 321: 1-4)
          Related to Volume I of memoirs. Includes photographs of Ardeshir, Fazlollah, Soraya, and Mohammad Reza Pahlavi.
        - Pahlavi Family, circa 1920s-1970 (Box-folder 321: 5)
          Includes photographs of Tadj ol-Molouk, Reza Shah, Mohammad Reza Pahlavi, Farah Pahlavi. Subjects include family vacations and imperial coronation.
        - Documents, circa 1940s, 1970s, 2000s (Box-folder 321: 6)
          Copies, prints, and originals of correspondence, articles, and memoranda. Material is in Persian, English, and French.
        - Memoir - Parts I-II, circa 1948-1980, 2008-2010 (Box-folder 323: 1-2, Box-folder 322: 1-7)
          Subjects: family (including birth of daughter), marriage to Princess Shahnaz, time spent in the U.S, father's funeral.
          Notable figures include: Former British Prime Minister Alec Douglas-Home, Bob Hope, Habib Bourguiba, Jr., Dean Rusk, Gerald Ford, Liza Minelli, Clement Atlee, Family (immediate family and Shah / Pahlavi family), Shah, Margot Fonteyn, Abdullah Malikyar, Dwight D. Eisenhower, (Vice President) Richard Nixon, and Queen Fawzia. Materials: prints, clippings, and mounted prints. Also includes correspondence from Farhad Shirzad regarding the printing of Zahedi’s memoir as well as a copy of the “Menu for Raphael and Mitra Saturday [sic] Wedding Dinner.”
        - 28 Mordad: Five critical days, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 323: 3-5)
          Related to Volume I. Depicts military and political figures (including Fazlollah); removal of statue; prints depicting coup and immediate aftermath.
        - Prime minister to resignation, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 324: 1-2, Box-folder 323: 6)
          Related to Volume I. Includes photographs of Fazlollah, Richard Nixon, and Mohammad Reza Pahlavi.
        - Engagement, Wedding, Mahnaz, 1956-1961 (Box-folder 324: 2-5)
          Related to Volume II. Includes photographs of Princess Shahnaz Pahlavi, Fazlollah Zahedi, Zohdi Zahedi, Princess Shams Pahlavi, Princess Ashraf Pahlavi, and Senator Mahmoud Jam.
        - First appointment in the United States, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 324: 6)
          Related to Volume II. Includes photographs of Fazlollah, Shahnaz, Mahnaz, the Shah, Dr. M. Vakil, Mrs. Vakil, Dr. A. A. Baher, Mr. N. Elghanayan. Mr. A. Ardalan, Mr. A. Elghanayan, Dwight D. Eisenhower, and Ambassador William Averell Harriman.
        - United Kingdom, circa 1960-1965 (Box-folder 325: 1-3)
          Related to Volume II. Includes photographs of Prince Philip, Queen Elizabeth II, Mahnaz, Shahnaz, Farhad Sepahbodi, Nubar Gulbenkian, Colonel Hossein Jahanbani, Mostafa Vasiqhi, Fereydoun Sotoudeh, Reza Hashemian, Ahmad Tehrani, Lord Louis Mountbatten and Lady Edwina Mountbatten.
        - Volume II photo captions, circa 2010 (Box-folder 325 :4-6)
          Photocopied photos with complete captions in Persian, with notes.
        - Minister of Foreign Affairs, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 326: 1, Box-folder 325: 7)
          Includes photographs of Mohammad Reza Pahlavi, Farah Diba Pahlavi, Heinrich and Wilhelmine Lubke, and King Hussein bin Talal.
        - Fawzia, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 326: 2)
          Includes copies of the album from the wedding for Fawzia and Mohammad Reza Pahlavi in 1939.
        - Second appointment in the United States and some photographs from the Shah's death in Egypt, 1971-1980 (Box-folder 326: 3)
          Includes photographs of Richard Nixon, Spiro Agnew, Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi, Senator Mike Mansfield, Elizabeth Taylor, Gerald R. Ford, Ronald and Nancy Reagan, and Polly Bergen.
      - Later albums, circa 2000-2016
        Includes original albums depicting Zahedi's travels, home in Switzerland, family, and various events attended, circa 2000-2016. Titles and descriptions in English and Persian.
        - Nowruz, 2003 (Box-folder 326: 4-6)
        - Montreux, 2010 (Box-folder 326: 7, Box-folder 327: 1-2)
        - Villa les Roses, 2014, 2016 (Box-folder 327: 3-6)
        - Ministry of Foreign Affairs Volume III, [?], Alec Home, and Me, etc., undated (Box-folder 328: 1-2)
        - Collected photos, undated (Box-folder 328: 3-4)
          Includes photocopies and original prints organized into two separate books/albums. Titles and descriptions in Persian.
        - Assorted albums, circa 2011-2015 (Boxes 329-332, Box-folder 328: 5)
          Contains several albums related to vacations, events, and Zahedi's home in Switzerland. Many of the albums include descriptions and accompanying negatives. Box 332 includes one roll of unprocessed film with a description taped to the outside of the canister in Persian.
    - Loose prints, circa 1950-2016 (Boxes 333-334)
      Includes prints, copies, photocopies, and negatives. Many appear related to the memoir albums, but it is unclear. Most of the photos in box 333 relate to the earlier years of Zahedi's life, while those in box 334 relate to later years. Note that there are some Ambassador-related photos in box 334.
  - Moving Images
  - Printed Matter, 1961-2015
    - Clippings, 1961-2012, undated (Box 335)
      Contains photocopies and originals of news articles and editorials. Also includes a book of collected articles from American newspapers on Iran in 1979.
    - Magazines, 1988-2015
      - Persian magazines, 1988-2015
        - Rah-E-Zendegi, 1988-2015 (Boxes 336-346)
        - Miscellaneous Persian magazines (Box-folder 346: 2-5)
      - French and English magazines, circa 2010-2014 (Box-folder 346: 6, Box-folder 347: 1)
        Subjects include U.S. foreign policy, Iranian affairs, and arts and culture.
    - Pamphlet in Persian (Box-folder 347: 2)
  - Oversize Material
  - Digital Files, 2002-2014
    Consists of digital files, including digital photographs and digital surrogates representing documents and photographs related to Ardashir Zahidi's work, friends, and family.
  - Digital photo albums (disks) (Box 348)